Simon Liu

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute. NIHBC 10 - CRC BG RM 3-2551 10 Center Dr Bethesda, MD 20892

III simon.liu@nih.gov - ☒ nhgri/mgb III simon@simonliu.dev - ⑤ simonliu.dev III simonliu.gov - ⑥ 0000-0002-1182-5492

Summary

I am a postbaccalaureate fellow at the National Institutes of Health interested in deep learning algorithms that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves applying natural language processing to public and private datasets to build models for extracting patient and language annotators. I am a member of the Medical Genomics Unit in the National Human Genome Research Institute.

Education

B.S., Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD. Focus on Biomedical Data Science

Also completed B.S. major requirements for Computer Science

Research Experience

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD. 07/2021 - present With Benjamin Solomon

08/2017 - 05/2021

12/2018 - 03/2020

J-2

J-1

C - 1

A-2

A-1

Software Engineer, Neuroplastic Surgery Research Laboratory, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, 02/2020 - 05/2021 MD. USA.

With Chad Gordon.

Received Provost's Undergraduate Research Award 2020-21 [1] [2]

Laboratory Assistant, STAR-ORC, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA. 07/2018 - 03/2020 With Junfang Wu

Research Analyst, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.

With Susan Hutfless

Research Assistant, Battle Lab, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 02/2018 - 09/2018
With Alexis Battle and Ben Strober

Publications

A list is also available on Google Scholar and Publons.

Journal Articles

Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., Khan, N., Cao, T., He, J., Lei, Z., Matyas, J. J., Sabirzhanov, B., Liu, S., Li, H., Stoica, B. A., Loane, D. J., Faden, A. I., & Wu, J. (2020). Delayed microglial depletion after spinal cord injury reduces chronic inflammation and neurodegeneration in the brain and improves neurological recovery in male mice. Theranostics, 10(25), 11376–11403. https://doi.org/10.7150/thno.49199
Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., He, J., Cao, T., Sabirzhanov, B., Li, H., Liu, S., Wu, L. J., & Wu, J. (2021). The voltage-

gated proton channel Hv1 plays a detrimental role in contusion spinal cord injury via extracellular acidosis-mediated neuroinflammation. Brain, behavior, and immunity, 91, 267–283. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.10.005

Conference Papers

Kenet, A., Mahadevan, E., Elangovan, S., Yan, J., Siddiq, K., **Liu, S.**, Ladwa, A., Narayanan, R., Dakkak, J., Benassi, T., Ng, K., & Manbachi, A. (2020). Flexible piezoelectric sensor for real-time image-guided colonoscopies: a solution to endoscopic looping challenges in clinic. Proc. SPIE 11315, Medical Imaging 2020: Image-Guided Procedures, Robotic Interventions, and Modeling, 1131520 (16 March 2020). https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2548873

Meeting Abstracts

Hutfless, S. M., Chu, D., **Liu, S.**, & Kalloo, A. N. (2020). Predictors of ERCP-associated infections in outpatient hospitals. Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, 91(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gie.2020.03.3314 Hutfless, S. M., Chen, P.-H., Miller, S. D., Josephson, M., Joseph, S., Urrunaga, N., Kedia, S., **Liu, S.**, Arya, N., Hobstetter, L., Persad, P., Yeretssian, G., & Brant, S. R. (2020). Would K50* by any other name smell so sweet? A systematic review of claims-based Crohn's disease case definitions. Gastroenterology, 158(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/s0016-5085(20)31712-1

Preprints

Duong, D., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Hanchard, S. L., **Liu, S.**, Solomon, B. D., & Waikel, R. L. (2021). Neural networks for classification and image generation of aging in genetic syndromes.

https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.12.09.21267472

Selected Honors

Linda Trinh Memorial Award, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA

05/2021

12/2020

11/2020

P-1

COVID-19 PPE Manufacturing Proposal: Consortium for 3D-Printed Headbands for Face Shields

With Yunonne Bai, Jacob Feitelberg, Katherine Hu, Sahana Kumar, Kirby Leo, James Li, Christopher Shallal, and Nicholas Zhang

Intuitive Surgical Best Project Award Runner Up, Deep Learning course, Johns Hopkins University,

Baltimore, MD, USA.

Project: Detection and Segmentation of Pneumothoraces in Chest X-ray.

With Fangchi Shao, Yixuan Huang, and Ameya Harmalkar.

Provost's Undergraduate Research Award, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.

Project: Implementing Electronic Beam Steering in an Implantable Ultrasound Device

With Chad Gordon. [1] [2]

Maryland Seal of Biliteracy, Maryland State Department of Education, Rockville, MD, USA.

06/2017

2022

2019

Sp 2021

Fa 2020

Selected Press

Stokel-Walker, Chris. "Amid war fears, archivists are racing to preserve Ukraine's internet" Input

Mag. February 18, 2022.

Calabresi, Kaitlyn. "Interview with Health 3D" TCO Labs. November 20, 2019.

Sangana, Neha. "Conference highlights student startups in Md." The Johns Hopkins News-Letter. 2018

November 15, 2018.

Entrepreneurship

VP of Manufacturing, Health 3D, LLC, Baltimore, MD, USA.

04/2018 - 05/2021

Built up manufacturing arm of healthcare education venture.

Selected into Social Innovation Lab 2018-2019 Cohort and Spring 2020 FUEL Accelerator Cohort.

Oversaw manufacturing pipeline of COVID-19 PPE for the Johns Hopkins Health System (feature article).

Teaching

Course Assistant

EN.500.113 Gateway Computing: Python, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University,

Baltimore, MD, USA.

EN.500.113 Gateway Computing: Python, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University,

Baltimore, MD, USA.

Selected Coursework

Undergraduate Computer Integrated Surgery I

Computer Integrated Surgery II

Machine Learning

Machine Learning: Deep Learning

Neuroengineering Lab

Cell and Tissue Engineering Lab

Biomedical Data Science

Precision Care Medicine I

Precision Care Medicine II

Computational Medicine: Cardiology

Computational Medicine: Cardiology Lab

Foundations of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

Metadata

This document lives online at simonliu.dev/markdown-cv/.

A downloadable version can be found at simonliu.dev/files/liu_cv.pdf.

Based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp.

MIT License.

Last updated: February 2022